Guide to the Housing Study Guild Records, 1929-1957, 1929-1941 (bulk)
Housing Study Guild Records, 1929-1957, 1929-1941 (bulk)
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Housing Study Guild Records, 1929-1957, 1929-1941
3333
Housing Study Guild.
1.4 cubic ft.
Publications, reports, and correspondence.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Publications, reports, and correspondence by or concerning the Housing Study Guild. Also, correspondence of Benjamin Macson Gruzen, council member of the Housing Study Guild, and publications of the National Association of Housing Officials, New York City Housing Authority and the United States Resettlement Administration.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The Housing Study Guild was founded in the summer of 1933 by Henry Wright, Lewis Mumford and Albert Mayer to serve as a center for study and research in the technical, economic and social problems of housing and community planning. It also served as a coordinating agency and clearing house for activities in these fields; as a library and reading room for published and unpublished material, the editing of current critical technical bulletins, abstract-translations of significant foreign technical material, and the publication of special reports on foreign housing policy, legislation, and financing methods; and as a laboratory for the training of young men in the technique of housing, research and critical formulation. The Guild, located at 101 Park Avenue, New York City, was financed through contributions of the Lavanburg Foundation, the Housing Association of New York, and individual and corporate memberships.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Publications, reports, and correspondence by or concerning the Housing Study Guild. Also, correspondence of Benjamin Macson Gruzen, council member of the Housing Study Guild, and publications of the National Association of Housing Officials, New York City Housing Authority and the United States Resettlement Administration.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Housing Study Guild.; Gruzen, Benjamin M.; Mayer, Albert.; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-; Wright, Henry.; National Association of Housing and Redevelopment Officials.; New York City Housing Authority.; United States. Resettlement Administration.
Subjects:
Sociology, Urban.; City planning.; City planning libraries.; Community development.; Housing research.; City planners.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Housing Study Guild Records, 1929-1957
  - National Association of Housing Officials, Chicago, Illinois, 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Printed materials including bulletins and the association's constitution.
  - Citizen's Housing Council of New York, Inc., 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Printed materials including the 1939 annual report.
  - Citizen's Housing Council of New York, Committee on City Planning and Zoning., 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed materials of the Committee; proposed revisions of the 1937 building zone resolution prepared by the New York City Planning Commission
    Printed materials of the CHC Subcommittee on Laws and Administration.
  - New York City Housing Authority. U.S. Work Projects Administration of the City of New York. Division of Foreign Housing Studies., 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4-9)
    Bibliographies and Indices of Special Subjects. Publications dealing primarily with European housing.
  - New York City Housing Authority., 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Publications deal primarily with public housing.
  - National Resources Committee., 1936 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    Printed publications dealing with urban development.
  - New York State Board of Housing., 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Published reports.
  - New York State Building Congress, Inc. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Resettlement Administration. Division of Suburban Resettlement., 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Includes a 1936 interim report, printed accessions lists of the library.
  - United States Housing Act of 1936., 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    U.S. Senate and House publications dealing primarily with the housing act of 1936.
  - Wagner-Steagall Housing Bill (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Regional Housing Studies., 1932-1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Miscellaneous publications dealing with housing and housing developments including reports on the Lavanburg Homes (NY) and the Michigan Blvd. Garden Apartments. (Chicago).
  - Miscellaneous publications and journals on housing management, low cost housing., 1933-1957 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous publications and journals on housing management, low cost housing., 1933-1957 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - U.S. Central Housing Committee, Subcommittee on Research and Statistics., 1936 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Housing index digests and a catalog of government documents related to housing.
  - U.S. Central Housing Committee. Housing Division., 1937 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    PWA published reports on European housing; includes a confidential report to the Housing Division.
  - U.S. Dept. of the Interior, Housing Authority. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Printed materials of the H.A. including a speech by Nathan Strauss.
  - U.S. Federal Emergency Administration of Public Works. Housing Division., 1936 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Report on the relationship between housing and delinquency; includes map of Washington, D.C., showing locations of delinquent children.
  - U.S. Federal Emergency Administration of Public Works, Housing Division., 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Printed materials including a report on slums in the U.S.
  - Housing Study Guild Bulletins (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Housing Study Guild. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Cost differential study of 2 floor vs. multi-floor apartments, part 2 (part 1 in mapcase.)
  - Housing Study Guild., 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Report on the Queens Bridge Dwellings (New York).
  - Housing Study Guild. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Maintenance report.
  - Housing Study Guild., 1934 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Drafts of reports on housing in the Netherlands and Belgium by Cornelis J.V. Devischer. Series F, no.4-5.
  - Housing Study Guild. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Draft of a report on housing in Austria by Paul Sechy, 1934. Series F, no.7; includes handwritten notes.
  - Housing Study Guild., 1934 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Draft of a report on housing in Spain by Charlotte H. Knapp. Series F, no. 9; includes finished illustrations.
  - Notes for the Spanish report. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Housing Study Guild., 1935 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Draft of a report on French housing by Charlotte H. Knapp.
  - Housing Study Guild. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Drafts of reports on housing in Sweden and Norway, by O.A. Madsen and C.J.V. Deuisscher. Series F, no.2 and 3
    Also includes an untitled draft of a second study of Sweden.
  - Housing Study Guild., c. 1934 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Untitled draft of study on housing in the USSR.
  - Report on Housing in Soviet Russia. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - English Housing report by Charlotte H. Knapp., 1934 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Report on Housing in Hungary, Paul S. Sechy., 1934 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Housing Study indexes. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Housing Study Guild (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Memos, budgets, agenda, etc.
  - Housing Study Guild Library. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Resettlement Administration Library. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Resettlement Administration Library. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence., 1932-1935 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Benjamin Gruzen correspondence., 1936 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Benjamin Gruzen correspondence., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - F.A.E.C.T. School., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Henry Wright Library., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Plan and Notes., 1931-1941 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - "Analytic Study of Cost Differentials for the 2 Story Flat and 2-3-4-6--8-10-12 Story Apartments. (Folder 1)
    (See Box 1, Folder 27 for Part 2)